SANTIAGO ARRÓNIZ PARRA

CURRICULUM VITAE

Ph.D. Student Department of Spanish & Portuguese Indiana University sarroniz@indiana.edu (812) 947-1039 355 North Jordan Avenue Global and International Studies Building 2160 Indiana University Bloomington, IN 47405

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research involve (1) phonological investigation of suprasegmental aspects of Spanish, specifically the intonational cues used to categorize meaning, and (2) natural language processing, in particular machine learning of natural language. I work mainly with Andalusian, Castilian, and Caribbean Spanish. Other areas of interest include second language phonology, language attitudes toward intonation, the role of suprasegmental features in information structure, dependency parsing, corpus analysis, and machine learning for natural language processing.

EDUCATION

Indiana University, Bloomington, IN (United States) *Ph.D.*, Hispanic Linguistics, August 2019 - Present *Master of Arts*, Hispanic Linguistics, May 2018

University of Seville, Seville (Spain)

Master of Arts, Linguistics, Literature, and Cultural Studies, June 2019 Bachelor of Arts, English Studies, June 2015

Manchester Metropolitan University, Manchester (United Kingdom)

 $Erasmus\ Exchange\ Program,\ Faculty\ of\ Languages,\ Linguistics\ and\ TESOL\ —$ Academic year 2013 - 2014

CURRENT PROJECTS

The perception of suprasegmental features of Spanish: categorizing sentence meaning

This project addresses the categorization of sentence meaning using pitch alignment, tonal rise, and final falls as perceptual cues. This study takes a Laboratory Phonology approach in which a perceptual experiment was developed to observe how speakers of different dialects of Spanish make use of different intonational cues to convey sentence meaning. Specifically, this project compares Andalusian (southern Spain) and Puerto Rican speakers.

The role of pitch height in the interpretation of sentence meaning

This preliminary study focuses on the role of pitch as the only perceptual cue for conveying up to three possible sentence meanings in Peninsular Spanish. A perceptual experiment was developed in which different modifications of the same word were included. The only change was the pitch height of the stressed syllable. The results seem to show that a low pitch is associated with a broad focus statement, and a high pitch with an echo yes/no question. However, a third category (narrow focus statement) located in the middle of the tonal range shows some variation among speakers.

SEÑAL: Computational Assessment of L2 Spanish compositions

SEÑAL is an ongoing collaborative project intended to evaluate different components of essays written by students of Spanish as a second language. Among other functions, currently SENAL can provide a lexical-syntactic analysis of the complexity of an L2 essay, information about the frequency of various grammatical forms (such as nouns, adjectives, adverbs, and various verb tenses), a spelling and grammatical agreement checker, and a text classifier using machine learning techniques.

EXPERIENCE

Associate Instructor - Department of Spanish & Portuguese

Indiana University (Bloomington, IN)

2016 - 2018; 2019 - Present

Teaching assignments:

- HISP-S 150: Elementary Spanish II (Fall 2016)
- HISP-S 200: Second-year Spanish I (Fall 2017; Spring 2018)
- HISP-S 250: Second-year Spanish II (Spring 2017; Fall 2019)
- HISP-S 280: Spanish Grammar in Context (Spring 2020)
- HISP-S 326: Introduction to Hispanic Linguistics (Fall 2020; Spring 2021)

Research Assistant - Department of Spanish & Portuguese

Prof. Erik Willis (Indiana University)

Summer 2020

Different tasks related to the phonetic analysis of different aspects of Spanish.

English Language Instructor

Kids&Joy Language School (Morón de la

2018 - 2019

Frontera, Spain)

Teaching assignments (CEFR):

- A1/A2: Elementary English for children (2 sections)
- B1: Low Intermediate English for teenagers (3 sections)
- B1: Low Intermediate English for adults (4 sections)
- B2: Upper Intermediate English for teenagers (2 sections)

IUHPFL Language Instructor

IU Honors Program in Foreign Languages

Summer 2018

Public Relations Coordinator, Literature Instructor.

Internship at the Office of International Services

University of Seville (Seville, Spain)

2015 - 2016

Tasks included administrative work, attention to international students, email management and technical support.

Internship at the Spanish Association for the Effects of Cancer Treatment

AEETC (Seville, Spain)

2014 - 2015

Tasks included the production and preparation of adapted materials for oncological children, as well as the development of a predictive text tool directed to those students in the scope of secondary education.

ADDITIONAL EDUCATION

Italian Language Course (Elementary): University of Seville, September 2012 - June 2013.

Attendance to Workshop Formación del Programa Sinergia: Organized by the University of Seville, November - December, 2014.

CAMPUS & COMMUNITY SERVICE

Graduate Student Advisory Committee (GSAC)

Indiana University, Bloomington (2020-2021)

Co-chair.

18th Diálogos Graduate Student Conference

Indiana University, Bloomington (February 26-27, 2021)

Conference organization.

Congreso Retorno al Español del Caribe REALEC 2020

Hosted via Zoom. Pontificia Universidad Católica Madre y Maestra, Santiago, Dominican Republic (November 4-7, 2020).

Co-host and technical support.

17th Diálogos Graduate Student Conference

Indiana University, Bloomington (February 28-29, 2020)

Panel moderator.

IWLC Working Papers in Linguistics Indiana University, Bloomington (2019 -Present) External reviewer.

3rd International Conference of the American Pragmatics Association Indiana University, Bloomington (November 4-6, 2016) Technical and organizational support.

COMPUTER SKILLS

Languages: Python, R, LATEX.

Operating Systems: Unix, Linux, Mac OSX, Windows.

Data Analysis: Praat, AntConc, RStudio, Qualtrics, scikit-learn, flair.

PUBLICATIONS Arróniz, S. (2019). Joke comprehension by Spanish B2 level learners of English. Master's Thesis. Universidad de Sevilla, Sevilla.

WORKING **PAPERS**

Arróniz, S. and Coulter-Kern, M. Lo aprecio mucho, pero... Teaching responses to invitations in intermediate level courses using computer mediated communication IULC Working Papers. Bloomington, IN. (under review)

MANUSCRIPTS

2016

Arróniz, S. Aspiración de /s/ en Posición Inicial de Sílaba: Un Estudio Sociolingüístico en el Habla Regional del Sur de España. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. Giving response to gratitude expressions in bilingual contexts: A contrastive analysis between American English and Spanish. (not submitted for publication)

2017

Arróniz, S. and Coulter-Kern, M. A study of the production of trills after heterosyllabic consonants in non-native Spanish learners. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. Africación de los grupos /st/, /kt/ y /pt/: Una evolución de la postaspiración en Andalucía. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. and Coulter-Kern, M. Fortición de la consonante palatal sonora: Un estudio explotatorio. (not submitted for publication)

2018

Arróniz, S. Intonational Patterns and Perception: A Contrastive Analysis between Peninsular and Puerto Rican Spanish. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. Inovação linguística na poesia de Mário de Sá-Carneiro. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. Estrategias de descortesía en el aula de español como L2. (not submitted for publication)

2019

Arróniz, S. The acquisition of intonation by L2 Spanish students (Proposal). (not submitted for publication)

2020

Arróniz, S. Computer-Assisted Language Learning: Testing Morphological Structures in L2 Spanish. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. and Coulter-Kern, M. Who is motivated to trill? A cross-sectional sociolinguistic study investigating the acquisition of trills following heterosyllabic consonants. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. Intonation and attitudes: Examining language attitudes toward Catalan by Peninsular Spanish speakers. (not submitted for publication)

Arróniz, S. High, or super-high, that is the question: Examining the role of pitch range in Peninsular Spanish (not submitted for publication)

PRESENTATIONS

2017

Arróniz, S. Giving response to gratitude expressions in bilingual contexts: A contrastive analysis between American English and Spanish. *14th Diálogos Graduate Student Conference*. Bloomington, IN. March 2017)

2018

Arróniz, S. and Coulter-Kern, M. Fortición de la consonante palatal sonora: Un estudio explotatorio. *15th Diálogos Graduate Student Conference*. Bloomington, IN. March 2018.

Arróniz, S. Africación de los grupos /st/, /kt/ y /pt/: Una evolución de la post-aspiración en Andalucía. *15th Diálogos Graduate Student Conference*. Bloomington, IN. March 2018.

Arróniz, S. Estrategias de descortesía en el aula de español como L2. *II Congreso internacional del español hablado* Valencia, Spain. October 2018.

2020

Arróniz, S., Hanson, S. and Lurito, A. Perception of Intonation in Peninsular Spanish: a pilot study. *Project proposal presented at PhlegMe in Fall 2020*. Hosted via Zoom. Bloomington, IN.

2021

Arróniz, S. Computer-Assisted Language Learning: Testing Morphological Structures in L2 Spanish. 13th Annual Graduate Portuguese and Hispanic Symposium. Hosted via Zoom. Georgetown, DC. February 2021.

Arróniz, S. and Restrepo, F. Text Classification for L2 Spanish Compositions. 18th Diálogos Graduate Student Conference. Bloomington, IN. February 2021.

PROFESSIONALIZATION

2020

Writing a Diversity Statement. Center for Innovative Teaching and Learning. Indiana University Bloomington.

Creating a Teaching Portfolio. Center for Innovative Teaching and Learning. Indiana University Bloomington.

Professionalization Workshop Series. Department of Spanish & Portuguese. Indiana University Bloomington.